<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document title="XP::Development::Writing SQL">
  <main>
    <content>
      <title>Writing SQL</title>
      <editor>$Id$</editor>
      
      <para>
        <caption>How to write good SQL</caption>
        <text>
          Modern PHP applications often have a database driven backend
          which can be used via the structured query language (SQL). Hence,
          we often find SQL statements within classes, in a script or in
          the source for a webpage.<br/>
          Just like a normal program, SQL also has to be written by many
          and must be understood by many, so we want to make sure SQL is
          written in a nice and clean way. It should - just like it is with
          program code - not be possible to tell who wrote the SQL just by
          looking at the code.<br/>
          This document gives an overview about a common way to write SQL,
          it is not a standard but a guideline (but should be complied with
          anyways).
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>SQL-Keywords</caption>
        <text>
          The XP database classes always prefix your queries with a SQL
          keyword whenever you use one of <tt>select</tt>, <tt>insert</tt>,
          <tt>update</tt> or <tt>delete</tt>, so you have to remove it from
          your query. This is simply to make sure noone writes an update
          within a <tt>select()</tt>-call. So, remove these keywords from
          the beginning of your statement.
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>Database API</caption>
        <text>
          The database API has been developed to provide an easy but 
          powerful way to use a database. It has some special-purpose 
          classes like e.g. <tt>DBTransaction</tt> which provides a
          way to control transactions. Use them!
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>Database classes</caption>
        <text>
          The framework allows for special classes that represent tables
          from a database. In many cases it may be better to use them than
          to write the plain SQL in the script.<br/>
          Of course, this is only true for selects that do not join more
          than one table.<br/>
          See ports/rdbms/classgen on how to create those database classes;
          see skeleton/net/xp-framework/db/caffeine/XPNews.class.php for an
          example what a class like these can look like.
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>Variable insertion</caption>
        <text>
          Almost every statement needs to contain values from
          variables from a script/program. Often programmers do not
          check their variables to make sure they are safe. Thus
          scripts are vulnerable to a technique called sql injection. With
          the XP database classes one does not have to check every
          value for malicious characters manually but he may give hints
          about the type of a variable to the class. It uses these hints
          to safely include the values at the given positions in the
          supplied statement and it will care for safe escaping if
          neccessary.<br/>
          With this technique you can write code more simple to read, so
          please use it. Additionally this way of inserting values from
          variables into your SQL makes your statements more beautiful
          and readable in your code. 
        </text>
      </para>
    
      <para>
        <caption>Use comments</caption>
        <text>
          Many SQL dialects have the ability to place comments directly
          inside your statement. If your rdbms offers such a possibility
          - use it. Comments help you to find a paramter or a value in 
          your code. Imaging a long INSERT-statement with INSERT table
          () VALUES () - syntax. Once the variable list grows, you'll have
          severe problems to find a value in the VALUES-part. With comments
          this would not be a problem:
          <code>
insert into foobar
  (primary_key,
  ts_init,
  valid_from,
  changedby)
values
  (%d,  -- primary key
  %s,   -- ts_init
  %s,   -- valid_from
  %s)   -- changedby
          </code>
          
          You see?
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>Indentation</caption>
        <text>
          Indentation is something many people argue about, because there 
          are many different indenting styles and sometimes coding standards
          force you to use a style you don't like. But indentation is imporant
          to let your code look good. We found the following style to be
          nice, thus we are recommending it:<br/>
          SQL keywords begin at the current depth of indentation, their
          parameters are listed below them, with one more level of
          indentatation depth. One parameter on one line with all additional
          modifiers (e.g. <tt>noholdlock</tt>).<br/>
          An exception to the rule is the <tt>WHERE</tt>-keyword which has
          its first parameter on the same line and any following restrictions
          on following lines, the prepended <tt>and</tt> should be indented
          with two spaces so all clauses begin on the same column.<br/>
          An example shows this:<br/>
          <code>
select
  a.category_id,
  a.count(*) as cnt
from
  auftrag a noholdlock,
  vertrag v noholdlock
where a.vertrag_id= v.vertrag_id
  and v.tarifgruppe_id= XYZ
  and a.category_id= 30001
  and a.valid_from > 'Jan 1 2003 0:00AM'
order by 
  a.category_id
having 
  a.count(*) > 1
          </code>
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>The aim</caption>
        <text>The "superior" target we follow with these instructions is to
          have a common way to write SQL statements. Like coding standards
          this SQL-writing, or  SQL-formatting guidelines are supposed to
          help this framework to be even more high quality code.<br/>
          In best-case one should not be able to tell who wrote the SQL.
        </text>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <caption>SQL and database performance</caption>
        <text>Good sql code should not only be written in an elegant manner
          but also be tweaked to get the most performance out of your rdbms.
          Rdbms often include facilities for tweaking a query. When you utilize
          a Sybase Server or the MSSQL rdbms, you can enable &qouot;debugging&quot;
          output by the option <tt>set showplan on|off</tt>. When enabled the
          server prints the plan of any query that is transmitted. Make sure
          your query is run on the available indices of the involved tabled. It 
          is even better to use clustered indices or primary keys of tables.
        </text>
      </para>
    </content>
  </main>
</document>
